The Life Of Muhammad ﷺ Madinan Period Volume 2
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki;
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْم۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
اَلْحَمْدُلِلَّهِ اَوَّلاً وَآخِرًا
اَلَّلهُمَّ اِنَّ نَحْمَدُكَ حَتَّى تَرْضَى وَ نَحْمَدُكَ عِنْدَ الرِّضَى وَ نَحْمَدُكَ بَعْدَ الرِّضَى
وَنُصَلِّيْ وَنُصَّلِّمْ عَلَى سَيِّدِ الْاَوَّلِيْنَ وَالْآخِرِيْنَ وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
اَلسَّلَامُ عَلَيْكُمْ وَرَحْمةُ الله وَبَرَكَاتُه
When the Armies disbanded, after the Battle of the trench,
The Messenger of Allah ﷺ said: Now, we will attack them, they will not attack us.
اَلْآنَ نَغْزُوهُمْ وَلاَ يَغْزُونَنَا
This marked the turning point in the Islamic history, of the new founded state
for the past five years the Muslims were engaged in a defensive battle with Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
defensive battle for survival.
Now, the tables are turned, it is Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), that will be struggling to survive,
it will be Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) who will, now be on the defensive.
Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) are the ones who attack the Muslims in Badr(بدر),
it was Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), who attacked in Uhud(أحَد),
it was Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) who attacked in Al-Khandaq(الخندق)
and that was their last attempt.
That was not because they were having a change of heart
or because they were now, somehow becoming more sympathetic of the Muslims,
it was simply because they were exhausted
they couldn't carry on this fight, any further.
The Muslims have out done them in patience, and perseverance
and they couldn't keep up with them.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ  would say a year from now as we will see
when we're talking about Al-Hudaybiyya(ألحديبية).
يَا وَيْحَ قُرَيْشٍ لَقَدْ أنهكتهم الْحَرْبَ
Woe to Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), war has exhausted them.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says in Surat Al-Imran(سورة العمران), in the last Ayah(آية),
يَا أَيُّهَا الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا اصْبِرُوا وَصَابِرُوا وَرَابِطُوا
وَاتَّقُوا اللَّهَ لَعَلَّكُمْ تُفْلِحُونَ۝
Isbiroo(إِصْبِرُوْا) means, be patient,
Sabiroo (صَابِرُوْا) in Sarf(صرف) in Arabic in the science of, what is called Sarf(صرف),
looks at the components of the word or the makeup of the word,
you see in the Ayah(آية) it says: Isbiroo(إصْبِرُوْا) Wa-Sabiroo(وَصَابِرُوْا),
Isbiroo(إصْبِرُوْا) Wa-Sabiroo(وَصَابِرُواْ) they both come from the same root word which is Sabr(صَبْر)
but (إصْبِرُوْا) is a command to be patient.
So, what is Sabiroo (صَابِرُوْا)?
Sabiroo( صَابِرُوْ) is in the Wazan(وَزَنْ) what they call the Wazan(وَزَنْ) of Mufaela(مفاعلة),
it is patience between two parties.
So, in Arabic for example, you have Musaria(مسارعه), Mudhariba(مضاربه), Muqatila(مقاتله)
here the Fael(فعل) the verb is not done by individual but it's between two parties.
So, as if Allahعَزّوجَلّ is telling us that even though you might be patient
but what if your enemy is more patient then you, you have to outdo them and patience,
so you have in the Ayah(آية) two commands from Allah,
one of them is to be patient and the other one is to outdo your enemy in patience,
Isbiroo(إصْبِرُوْا) Wa-Sabiroo(وَصَابِرُوْا).
And that is what the Muslims did and it paid off, now.
After Badr(بدر) and Uhud(أحَد) and Al-Khandaq(ألخندق),
now it is Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) who will be on the defensive because the Muslims wore them out, the Muslims tired them.
And now Rasool Allah ﷺ  is saying;
اَلْآنَ نَغْزُوهُمْ وَلاَ يَغْزُونَنَا
Now, we will conquer them, they will not conquer us, we will not attack them, they will not attack us.
Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) was never again, able to bring together an army to invade Madina
that's it, he has done his best, to the extent that he was able,
same with his people, his followers in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), that was the best they could pull off.
The 10,000 strong army of Al-Khandaq(ألخندق).
It was a failure in the end because of the supernatural events that occurred, the wind and the soldiers of Allah.
وَمَا يَعْلَمُ جُنُودَ رَبِّكَ إِلَّا هُوَ
Only Allah knows His soldiers, we don't know the soldiers of Allah, anything can be a soldier of Allah.
Sometimes things that are blessings, things that they are the reasons for life, could be a soldier of Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
like water for example was a soldier of Allah, it killed Firaoun(فرعون),
a mosquito killed Namrood(نمرود),
the earth swallowed up Qaroon(قارون),
wind is a soldier of Allahعَزّوجَلّ, it destroyed nations, thunderbolts.
So, anything in this universe can be a soldier of Allah, we don't know soldiers of Allah that are around us.
With this the Muslims ended a very difficult period of defending their mere existence and holding on to their base.
The Muslims even though we say that the establishment of the Islamic State was with Hijrah(هجرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
but those were very, very difficult days the initial years in Madina were years of fear, were years of hiding, were years of insecurity.
We shouldn't think that this was a flourishing strong Islamic State,
it was in a very difficult, predicament, Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) from one side the Yahood(يهود) from the other,
the Bedouins from the third, very difficult time on the Muslims.
Sahabah(صحابه) used to say we would sleep with our arms next to us, we wouldn't feel security.
So, these first five years were very difficult,
but the Muslims held on strong, they have Sabr(صبر) in Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
But now the Muslims will move on to occupy new positions.
The next five years are going to be years of expansion,
the move from the defensive Jihad(جهاد) to the offensive one has taken place.
In these next five years, dear brothers and sisters, we will see an exponential growth of Islam
and some important events occurring.
The key events which we will talk about In sha Allah Ta'ala(اِنْشاءالله تعالى),
we ask Allah to give us the ability to go through the remainder of the five years of Seerah(سيرة), and to make this beneficial.
We ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ to give us beneficial knowledge.
اَلَّهُمَّ اِنَّا نَسْالُكَ عِلْمًا نَافِعَ وَ نَعَوْذُبِكَ مِنَّ عِلْمِ لَّايَنْفَعُ
These key events are going to be the,
Truce of Al-Hudaybiyya(ألحديبية) and the sixth year of Hijrah(هجرة),
the Battle of Khaybar(خيبر) and the seventh year of his Hijrah(هجرة).
The Battle of Maota(موته), the opening of Makkah,
The Battle of Hunain(حنين) and At-At-Taef(اَلطَّائِف) in the eighth year,
and then the Battle of Tabook(تبوك) and the farewell Hajj(حَجْ), in the ninth year.
And finally, the greatest event of all, the greatest, calamity that has ever befell, the Muslim Ummah(امة)
and that's the death of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And then we'll cover various other smaller events in between.
We'll start with some events that happened between Al-Khandaq(ألخندق) and Al-Hudaybiyya(الحديبية) within the fifth year of Hijrah(هجرة).
We talked in the previous set of lectures, about the assassination of Ka'ab Ibn Ashraf(كعب إبن أشرف)
and we said that Ka'ab Ibn Ashraf(كعب إبن أشرف) was a Jewish leader,
very rich man held an important position, among the people in Hijaz(حجاز), and he was a very eloquent poet
and he used to use this poetry,
and poetry we talked about the importance of it,
in the days of Jahilliyah(جاهلية), it was the media of the day
and Ka'ab Ibn Ashraf(كعب إبن أشرف) would use this poetry of his, to defame the Muslims and talk against Rasool Allah ﷺ.
If one would read in the history of the Jahilliyah(جاهلية) in Arabia,
one would see that a particular line of history would bring a ruin to a tribe, it would ruin their reputation.
Just like a documentary or, or a particular article in The Big newspaper would do today.
In fact, probably even the effect of poetry was greater.
So, Ka'ab Ibn Ashraf(كعب إبن أشرف), one of the things he was doing he was even talking about the Muslim women and Muslims then,
and this should be the case with the Muslims all the time,
should stand up, for the rights of Al-Muslimaat(ألمسلمات) and defend Al-Muslimaat(ألمسلمات),
and we know of many, stories in our history of that occurring
for example the Battle of Bannu Qainuqah(بنوقينقاع), against the Jewish tribe of Bannu Qainuqah(بنوقينقاع) in Madina was
because of their attack on a Muslim woman, when they uncovered her
and we know what happened with Al-Motasim(ألمعتصم), the Muslim Khalifah(خليفه) in Daulat-Al-Abbasia(ألدولة العباسيهِ),
when the woman called to him Wa-Motasimah(وا معتصماہ) when the Romans attacked.
Then he mobilize an entire army to go and defend her.
So, Ka'ab Ibn Ashraf(كعب إبن أشرف) was speaking against Muslim women
and it's said that he has spoken about Umm Al-Fadhal(أم الفضل),
the wife of Al-Abbas Bin Abdul-Muttalib(ألعباس بن عبدالمطلب), the uncle of Rasool Allah ﷺ .
Anyway, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
مَنْ لِّيْ بِكَعْب اِبْنِ اَشْرَفْ فَاِنَّه’قَدْ آذَّى اللهَ وَ رَسُوْله
Who will get rid of Ka'ab Ibn Ashraf(كعب إبن أشرف) because he has harmed Allah and His messenger.
Muhammad Ibn Maslima رضي الله عنه volunteered, for this special operation along with some other members of his tribe.
What tribe was this?
This tribe was Al-Aos(ألأوس).
So, it was a Al-Aos(ألأوس) who killed Ka'ab Ibn Ashraf(كعب إبن أشرف).
Now, as one of Al-Ansaar(ألانصار) or the one of the descendants of Al-Ansaar(ألانصار) said:
In a narration mentioned by Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر)
that Al-Aos Wal Khazraj(اَلْأوس وَالْخزْرج) were like two stallions, competing in front of Rasool Allah ﷺ .
Whenever, one clan would do something in service of Rasool Allah ﷺ ,
the other clan would not want them to take that advantage alone, and would try to do something similar.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), we see that they had competition,
they had this spirit of competition, but it wasn't in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا),
it wasn't and who would be more successful in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا),
who would make more money, who would hold a higher position,
as we see competition now, in the material world in the materialistic, capitalistic world
and way of life that the West is promoting.
You know, the success philosophy, in the West today
and the competition for success that the West is presenting to the world today, is a materialistic one.
And it holds no value in the Islamic view of things.
Because success in the West is defined in, purely materialistic terms.
But the success in Islam is how close to Allahعَزّوجَلّ you are?
So, a person could be totally unknown in Duniya(دنيا), he could be very poor,
nevertheless, he is very successful because he's close to Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
And a classical example that one could give of that is Al-Owais Al-Qarni(إويس ألقرني).
I mean Owais Al-Qarni(إويس ألقرني) , was a person that was ambiguous, people didn't know him.
And when Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) ask the delegation that came from the tribe of Owais Al-Qarni(إويس ألقرني)
the name of his tribe was Muraad(مراد), it's a tribe in Yemen.
And when Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) asked about him, they said
(I mean, the way they talked about him is, as if they were surprised, why the Ameer-Ul-Momineen(امير المؤمنين),
why the Khalifah(خليفه) would ask about such a simple person.)
I mean, who is he, who is Owais Al-Qarni(إويس ألقرني)?
Nobody knew him, except his relatives and the people who lived with him.
And they saw him as simple, normal human being.
He wasn't a leader of a Muslim army.
He wasn't an Ameer(امير) of a Jama'at(جماعة),
he wasn't a famous scholar or a Imam(امام),
he was just a simple human being.
But there was something in his heart that made him special,
in fact, he was so special that Rasool Allah ﷺ told the Sahabah(صحابه),
that when a delegation comes from Yemen from the tribe of Muraad(مراد).
There will be man with them, his name is Owais Al-Qarni(إويس ألقرني),
if you see him than ask him, to ask Allah to forgive you,
this man is, so special that you should ask him for Dua(دُعَا),
he was one of the Saliheen(صالحين) one of the Aouliyaa(أولياء) of Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
and whose Rasool Allah ﷺ telling it to?
He is telling it to the Sahaba(صحابه) the greatest generation that ever lived.
And Owais Al-Qarni(إويس ألقرني) is not a Sahabi(صحابي), he is a Taba'ee(تابعي)
because he never saw Rasool Allah ﷺ,
he wanted to make Hijrah(هجرة) to Rasool Ullah but because his mother was alone and ill,
he stayed behind with her and Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away.
So, he never had a chance to meet him, but Rasool Allah ﷺ knew him and talked about him.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) when he met with Owais Al-Qarni(إويس ألقرني) he told him,
ask Allah to forgive me.
Back to this competition, so Al-Aos Wal Khazraj(اَلْأوس وَالْخزْرج) would compete with each other.
What was their competition about, it was about Al-Aakhira(آخرة),
who would serve Rasool Allah ﷺ better,
and in this case, it was because Al-Aos(ألأوس) had the honor of assassinating Ka'ab Ibn Ashraf(كعب إبن أشرف),
who would defame Rasool Allah ﷺ,
Al-Khazraj(اَلْخَزرج), didn't want to be left out on this.
They wanted to do something similar.
So, they had a meeting and they discussed the issue amongst themselves
and they came up with the name of Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع) as a good candidate or performing such an operation against,
and they presented the idea to Rasool Allah ﷺ and Rasool Ullah approved it.
Abdullah Bin Ateeq(عبدالله بن عتيق) was the man appointed to lead this special operations group, one of Al-Khazraj(اَلْخَزرج)
and they set out to infiltrate deep into the land of Khaybar(خيبر).
This is before the Battle of Khaybar(خيبر) and Khaybar(خيبر) was the stronghold of the Jews.
Nevertheless, the courage of the Sahabah(صحابه) was to lead them, deep into the land of Khaybar(خيبر)
and Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع) lived in a fortress of his.
He wasn't living in a normal house, he was living in a palace and it was a fortress.
So, they marched out and they arrived at the gates of the fortress of Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع) .
Now, how would they get in?
Abdullah Bin Ateeq(عبدالله بن عتيق) played a trick against the Yahood(يهود).
In a narration and there are two narrations of this in Al-Bukhari(البخاري).
In one narration it says that, these Yahood(يهود), they lost a donkey,
so they opened the gates and some men came out to fetch out this donkey,
Abdullah Bin Ateeq(عبدالله بن عتيق) stood next to the wall.
And then he sat down and covered himself, as if he was responding to the call of nature,
pretended this in front of Al-Yahood(اليهود).
So what they thought is that he came out from the fortress.
Because in those days, they didn't have the restrooms inside their dwellings, they would go outside
and they would go, far away from their houses to respond to the call of nature.
So, they thought that he came out of the fortress to respond to the call of nature,
so when they went in they said;
ياعبدالله
o servant of Allah, if you want to come in, then now is the time.
So, he walked in, normally, the trick that he played on them worked.
So, now he was inside the fortress, while all of his companions were outside.
He told them to wait outside for him.
So, now he was in.
He hide in a donkey stall, and he was observing the gatekeeper
and was able to see where he would hide the keys.!
In one narration it says: They were hung on a wooden peg
and another narration, it says they were in a niche, in the wall.
Anyway Abdullah Bin Ateeq(عبدالله بن عتيق) said, that the men went on to have dinner with Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع),
so he remained in hiding, until all of these men left and the lights were turned off.
It was a very dark night,
Abdullah Bin Ateeq(عبدالله بن عتيق) went and fetched out the keys
and Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) all  of the keys were together, all of the keys for the fortress,
the gate of the fortress and the keys for the Palace of Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع), they were all there,
so now he had the keys with him.
So, he would open the doors and then he would lock them from inside.
Therefore, if anyone came in, to help Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع), he would find that the gates are closed
and the keys are not there, so he would open every door and lock it.
Now, this is a double edged sword, yes it would prevent people from coming in to help him,
but it would also hinder the escape of Abdullah Bin Ateeq(عبدالله بن عتيق)
but anyway, this is what he did.
until he made it into the inner chambers of Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع).
Now, he is with Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع) in the same room and Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع) is asleep, and the lights are turned off.
Tayyeb(طيب), How is he going to find out his location?
He can see nothing.
Now, what did Abdullah Bin Ateeq(عبدالله بن عتيق) do?
He just called out, he said: Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع).
It takes a lot of courage to do such a thing, it's a terrifying thing, to call out for someone, in such a situation,
but also on the other hand it's more terrifying for Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع) to hear this man calling him, inside his own bedroom.
So, Abdullah Bin Ateeq(عبدالله بن عتيق) is calling Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع).
Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع) woke up and said: Who are you?
Abdullah Bin Ateeq(عبدالله بن عتيق) said;
So I struck with my sword at the source of the voice, he can't see anything he just called him
and the reason he did so he wanted the man to speak, so he can recognize the source of the voice and attack it,
so he struck with his sword at the source of the voice, he said:
فَلَمْ اُغْنِ عَنْه’ شَيْئَا
He said: My blow was futile,
yes he did hit him but it wasn't accurate enough strike and obviously, there's confusion in such a circumstance,
so it didn't kill him.
Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع), yelled out for help, he screamed out.
What did Abdullah Bin Ateeq(عبدالله بن عتيق) do?
Ya'ani Masha Allah(يعني ماشاءالله) Abdullah Bin Ateeq رضي الله عنه,
he had very good response and intelligence on the spot, thinking on his feet,
when Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع) called out for help,
Abdullah Bin Ateeq(عبدالله بن عتيق), he retreated and then he came back changing his voice
and said:  Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع) what do you need?
Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع) said: Woe on to your mother, there's a man right here and he struck me with his sword.
So, Abdullah Bin Ateeq(عبدالله بن عتيق) he struck him again,
again at the source of the voice.
Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع) called out for help again,
Abdullah Bin Ateeq(عبدالله بن عتيق), retreated another time came in changing his voice
and said: Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع) what do you need?
He said: Woe on to your mother, there's a man in here, trying to kill me.
Abdullah Bin Ateeq(عبدالله بن عتيق) said: This time,
I came to him and he was lying on his back.
Now he was already struck with a sword two times,
now he was laying on his back still alive, but laying on his back.
Abdullah Bin Ateeq(عبدالله بن عتيق) said;
This time, I thrust my sword into his stomach, until I found out the bone and then I cracked it.
What bone are we talking about?
He struck the spinal cord.
So, that's it. He said: I heard the bone crack, meaning that the man is dead.
If the spine is broken, then it's certain death.
So, now Abdullah Bin Ateeq(عبدالله بن عتيق) said; I retreated.
Now, the inner chambers, his bedroom of Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع) was in the upper level
and there was a wooden ladder that would lead up to it.
When Abdullah Bin Ateeq(عبدالله بن عتيق) was coming down, in this ladder or stairs.
He said: I came down and in my confusion,
I thought that I have hit the last step of the ladder, when there was one more left,
so he fell down and he broke his leg.
He said and then I made it out to my companions
and told them that, I have killed Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع).
But Abdullah Bin Ateeq(عبدالله بن عتيق) Subhaan Allah,
he still wanted to make sure definitely that he is dead,
so he told his companions, to go back and deliver the good news to Rasool Allah ﷺ
and I'm going to hang behind and wait, until I hear the announcement of his death,
keep in mind that he broke his leg, so he stayed behind and he heard the news of, the death of Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع).
In the narration of Ibn Is'haqq(اِبْنِ اِسْحَاقْ)
he said: I heard his wife come to Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع) and say;
فَاضَ وَ اِلَهَ يَهُوْدْ
He is dead in the name of the God of the Jews.
What did Abdullah Bin Ateeq(عبدالله بن عتيق) say?
And I want you to pay attention to his words. He said;
And I swear, I never heard words sweeter to my ears than those.
And we'll get back to this statement.
Why was Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع) killed?
Ibn Hajar(إبن حجر) says;
وَكَانَ اَبُوْ رَفِعَ يُؤذِيْ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وَيُعِيْنُ عَلَيْهِ،
وَذكَرَ اَبْنُ عَائِذ مِنْ طَرِيْقِ الْاَسْوَدْ عَنْ عُرْوَةْ اَنَّه’ كَانَ مِمَّنْ اَعَانَ غَطَفَانَ و غَيْرَهُمْ مِنْ مُشْرِكِي الْعَرَبْ
مِنْ الّمَالِ الْكَثِيْرُ، عَلَى رَسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
Ibn Hajar(إبن حجر) says: Abu Rafiaa(ابورافع) used to harm Rasool Allah ﷺ  and assist against him
and Ibn Aaiz(إبن عائذ) said, that he was one of those,
who supported the Ghatafaan(غطفان) and other polytheistic Arabs, with money to fight Rasool Allah ﷺ .
So, his support was financial support and also by word.
Another event that happened within this period is the assassination of Khalid Ibn Sufiyan Ibn Nubih Al-Hudhali(خالد إبن سفيان إبن نُبَيح الهذلي),
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
اِنَّه’ قَدْ بَلَغَنِيْ اَنَّ خالد بن سفيان بن نُبَيح الهذلي
يَجْمَعَ لِي الْنَّاسِ لِيَغْزُونِيْ وَهُوَ بِعُرَنَة فَأتِهِ فَاقْتُلْه
I have been informed that Khalid(خالد) is gathering a force of men to attack me,
he is at Urana(عرانة) go to him, and kill him.
Khalid Ibn Sufiyan(خالد إبن سفيان) was an outstanding leader of his people,
he was one of those charismatic figures who have the ability to mobilize men
and to make out of nothing, something.
He was successful leader, he belong to the tribe Hudhail(هذيل),
Hudhail(هذيل) are Bedouins in Hijaaz(حجاز) and they're famous as being very eloquent.
قَالُوْ هُدَيْل اَشْعَرَالْعَرَبْ
They were the best poets of the Arabs
and they lived on the outskirts of Makkah.
Khalid Ibn Sufiyan(خالد إبن سفيان) was mobilizing men to fight Rasool Allah ﷺ,
here we were in a situation, where the people were in need of a leader and the leader was Khalid Ibn Sufiyan(خالد إبن سفيان).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ did not see the need, to fight his army
but to preemptively attack and get rid of Khalid Ibn Sufiyan(خالد إبن سفيان)
because if he does so, he would avoid a lot of bloodshed.
If Khalid Ibn Sufiyan(خالد إبن سفيان) is out of the arena, Hudhail(هذيل) are not going to fight him,
unlike with Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), the fight with Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) did not depend on leadership.
The people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) were going to fight regardless,
when Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل) was there, they fought
and after he was killed they carried on the fight in fact the fight only became worse, after Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل) was killed.
But here at the situation was different,
so we find that Rasool Allah ﷺ never targeted the leadership of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) with special operations to assassinate them
but he did this with some of the leaders of Al-Yahood(اليهود)
and he did it also with Khalid Ibn Sufiyan(خالد إبن سفيان)
because this is going to avoid killing other people,
it's gonna prevent, a larger battle escalating, and more war happening.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Go and get rid of Khalid Ibn Sufiyan(خالد إبن سفيان),
Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس), never met, Khalid Ibn Sufiyan Al-Hudhali(خالد إبن سفيان الهذلي) in his life,
so he told Rasool Allah ﷺ: How can I recognize him, give me a sign.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
اِذَا رَاَيْتَه’شَعَرْتَ(وَجَدْتُ) لَه’قَشَعِرَيْرَةَ
When you see him, you will shiver.
Now, Allah Ho Alam(الله اعلم) was this shiver because Khalid Ibn Sufiyan(خالد إبن سفيان) had such a great presence
or was is going to be a special sign, just then, for Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس) to recognize him,  Allah Ho Alam(الله اعلم).
But regardless Khalid Ibn Sufiyan(خالد إبن سفيان) was a special individual.
Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس) moved out, he was alone, an army of his own.
This is the courage that Sahaba رضي الله عنهم had,
and he's gonna travel deep into enemy territory, in Urana(عرانة) next to Makkah,
so he made it there and he found out the location of the army camp,
where Khalid Ibn Sufiyan(خالد إبن سفيان) is gathering the men.
He saw him and he felt shiver, the sign that Rasool Allah ﷺ mentioned
and Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس) said: I never shivered from anyone in my life.
This was the first time that he ever felt such a shiver.
It was time for As-Salaat-Ul-Asr(الصلاة العصر) and Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس) said;
وَخشِيْتُ اَنْ تَكُوْنَ بَيْنِيْ وَبَيْنَهُ مُّجَاوَلَهْ تَشْغَلْنِيْ عَنِّ(تَمْنَعْنِيْ مِنَّ) الصَّلاةْ
He said: I feared that there might be a conflict between me and him that would prevent me from Salah(صلاة).
Meaning this conflict could take time and wouldn't be able to pray, so what did he do
he prayed while he was walking towards his target.
وَكُنْتُ اُوْمِىءُ لِلرَّكُوْعِ وَالسُّجُوْدْ بِرَأسِي
And I would make Sujood(سجود) and Rakooh(ركوع) by movements of my head.
So, he walked up to him and greeted him,
Khalid Ibn Sufiyan(خالد إبن سفيان) said;
مَنِ الرَّجُلْ
Who is the man.?
قَالَ: اَنَا رَجُلٌ مِّنَّ الْعَرَبْ سَمِعَ بِكَ وَ بِجَمْعِكَ لِهَذَالرَّجُلْ
I am a Bedouin, I'm a man from amongst the Arabs who heard about you and you're gathering a force for this man,
he said;
اَنَا فِيْ ذَالِكْ
That's what I'm doing, he said: I came to follow you,
so then he held the conversation with him to break the ice
and when Khalid Ibn Sufiyan(خالد إبن سفيان) was comfortable with Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس)
and the opportune moment arrived,
Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس) struck, Khalid Ibn Sufiyan(خالد إبن سفيان) and killed him.
He walked away and he said: Tarakat-Hoo(تَرَكَتْه’) ,
I left him with his woman crouched over him,
Rasool Allah ﷺ greeted Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس) by saying,
أَفْلَحَ الْوَجْه
May your face be successful.
Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس) said;
أَفْلَحَ الْوَجْهُكَ يَا رَسُول الله
May your face be successful too.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ took him in to his house and gave him a stick.
Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس) walked out without saying a word.
And what was the stick for?
Why did Rasool Allah ﷺ  give it to him?
What is he gonna do with it?
Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس)  dare not to ask.
They were very shy, in dealing with Rasool Allah ﷺ, so he just walked out without saying a word.
This was the gift that Rasool Ullah gave him, a stick.
So, his people told him, what is the stick.?
He said: Rasool Ullah gave it to me.
Why did they give it to you?
He said: I don't know?
They said: Go back and ask him!
He went back to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
O Rasool Ullah, Why did you give me the stick?
He said;
آيَةً تَكُوْنُ بَيْنِيْ وَبَيْنَكَ يَوْمَ الْقِيَامَةْ اِنَّا اَقَلَّ النَّاسِ يَوْمَئِذٍ اَلْمُتَخَصِّرُوْنَ
He said this is a sign between me and you on the Day of Judgment,
there will be very few that day, with something, to lean upon.
Rasool Ullah gave him the stick as a gift,
so that on the Day of Judgment it will be a sign between him and Rasool Ullah.
Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس) coupled that stick with his sword, he kept it with his sword,
and then in his will, he asked that, the stick be buried with him.
So, it was put inside his coffin with him,
so that on the Day of Judgment, when he's resurrected, he will pick up that stick and go to Rasool Allah ﷺ
and it will be a sign between him and Rasool Ullah, on that very difficult day,
when there will be very few people with something to lean upon.
And this Rawayah(رواية) is in Masnad Imam Ahmad(مسند اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ).
One important lesson, brothers and sisters from this story,
The importance of Salah(صلاة),
the thing that concerned, Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس), when he was walking towards Khalid Ibn Sufiyan(خالد إبن سفيان) was Salaat-Ul-Asr(صلاةالعصر).
And the thing that concerned, the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم,
when Rasool Ullah, was talking to them about the signs of the end of time, when he was talking about Ad-Dajjal(الدجال)
and that one day of Ad-Dajjal(الدجال), will be like a year,
what did the Sahabah(صحابه) say?
How is that explained, physically?
Can you give us the astronomy explanation of how that is possible?
What did they say? They said;
هَلْ تَكْفِيْنَا فِيْهِ صَلَاةَ يَوْمْ
Is it's enough for us to pray in that day, the five daily prayers, prayers of one day?
They were thinking about Salah(صلاة),
and Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن انيس) in this life and death situation,
in this confusing situation, a person in that situation would be perplexed,
and as we just said, that his body shivered when he saw this man,
but, Salah(صلاة), Salah(صلاة), Salah(صلاة) he prayed, walking towards him.
Brothers and Sisters, there's no excuse in leaving Salah(صلاة)
if you don't have money, you're excused from paying Zakat(زكواة).
If you're ill, you're excused from fasting and you can play a Fidyah(فدية) instead.
If you don't have the financial ability and the road to Hajj(حَجْ) is not safe
you don't have to make Hajj(حَجْ),
but there is no situation in which a Muslim is excused from Salah(صلاة).
Even in the battlefield, we have to pray and we're given the Fiqh(فقه) of it, in Salaat-Ul-Khauf(صلاة الخوف).
In fact, the Sahabah(صحابه) considered Salah(صلاة) to be so important.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) used to say; that if a Muslim leaves one Salah(صلاة) intentionally then he has disbelieved.
We know that after that Ulema(علماء) discussed the issue of the Kuffr(كفر) of Taarik-Us-Salah(تارك الصلاة),
whether the one who leaves Salah(صلاة) is Kafir(كافر) or not
and one can go back to the books Fiqh(فقه) to see, what they said about that?
It's the opinion of Imam Ahmad(اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ) that if the person leaves it out of laziness,
than he is a Kafir(كافر), while the other Ulema(علماء) said;
that Muslims Kafir(كافر) only, if he leaves it intentionally.
Anyway this is not the place to discuss this issue but, it's very important, it's the most important Ibadah(عبادة),
so we should never dismiss our Salah(صلاة)
and for those Muslims because of their employment, leave for example Salat-Ul-Jum'ah(صلاةالجمعه),
or they leave some Salawaat(صلوات), we say to them, It'taqillah(إتقى الله), Fear Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
Abdullah Bin Unais(عبدالله بن أنيس), in this situation that is more important than your employment,
more dangerous than your situation, and he did not leave Salah(صلاة), so we should never leave Salah(صلاة).
Next event that happened within this period is regarding Zainab Bint Jahash(زينب بنت جحش).
Zainab Bint Jahash رضي الله عنها, Al-Assadiyyah(ألاَسَدِيْةَ) from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
She was the sister of Abdullah Bin Jahash(عبدالله بن جحش),
and we talked about his story in the earlier lectures
and her mother is Umaimah Bint Abdul-Muttalib(عميمه بنت عبدالمطلب), the sister of Hamza(حمزه),
so her mother is the aunt of Rasool Ullah, which makes her, his cousin.
Zainab Bint Jahash رضي الله عنها, Rasool Allah ﷺ visited her and he proposed to her marriage to his adopted son,
Zaid Bin Harissa(زيد بن حارثه).
Zaid Bin Harissa(زيد بن حارثه) was a slave.
And he's asking, Zainab Bint Jahash(زينب بنت جحش), who comes from the nobility of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) to marry a slave.
Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to break the barriers of discrimination and racism that existed
and he wanted to start among his own family
and ask that Zaid Bin Harissa(زيد بن حارثه) marry his own cousin Zainab Bint Jahash(زينب بنت جحش).
She said: No,
He(ﷺ) said: Yes, you will marry her.
She said: O Messenger of Allah, let me think about it and while they were talking, the Ayah(آية) was revealed,
وَمَا كَانَ لِمُؤْمِنٍ وَلَا مُؤْمِنَةٍ إِذَا قَضَى اللَّهُ وَرَسُولُهُ أَمْرًا أَنْ يَكُونَ لَهُمُ الْخِيَرَةُ مِنْ أَمْرِهِمْ ۗ
وَمَنْ يَعْصِ اللَّهَ وَرَسُولَهُ فَقَدْ ضَلَّ ضَلَالًا مُبِينًا۝
"It is not fitting for a believer, man or woman when a matter has been decided by Allah
and His Messenger to have any option about their decision,
if anyone disobeys Allah and His Messenger, he is indeed on a clearly wrong path.
If our desires are contrary to something that Rasool Allah ﷺ wants us to do,
we still do what Rasool Allah ﷺ wants us to do.
And it's important that we don't follow our whims and desires
but we follow the Sunnah(سنة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
what excuse do we have in not following His Sunnah(سنة).
What excuse, Do we have in not following the law of Allahعَزّوجَلّ, just because we don't like it,
just because it didn't suit our Ahwa'a(اَهْوَاء), our whims and desires.
We are slaves of Allahعَزّوجَلّ and we are followers of Muhammadﷺ
and whatever, we are told to do, we do it's not up to us,
so Zainab Bint Jahash(زينب بنت جحش), when this Ayah(آية) was revealed,
she said: I accept him as a husband.
لَا اَعْصِيْ رَسُوْل الله وَقَدْ زَوَجْتَه’ نَفْسِيْ
I will not disobey Rasool Allah ﷺ and I marry him myself.
But Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) things didn't work out, there was no compatibility,
after a year they were divorced.
Zaid Bin Harissa(زيد بن حارثه) was coming to Rasool Allah ﷺ and complaining about his wife.
He wasn't happy with her and she wasn't happy with him.
But Rasool Allah ﷺ would told him;
اِتَّقِ اللهَ وَ اَمْسِكْ عَلَيْكَ زَوْجَكْ
He said: Fear Allah and keep your wife, but things just couldn't continue on.
So, divorce was a must and the marriage was ended after a year.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ married her and that caused the storm of talk against Rasool Allah ﷺ.
In Arabia It was a no-no for a man to marry the wife of his adopted son.
Adoption was serious than, this before it was made Haram(حرام) in Islam.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ adopted Zaid(زيد) and he was called Zaid Ibn Muhammad(زيد ابن محمد).
So, now, all of the rules of Sharia(شريعة) that apply between a son and his father
applied between Muhammadﷺ and his son Zaid(زيد).
And one of the rules that existed in those days is that a man can never married the wife of his adopted son.
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ wanted to break this tradition among the Arabs
and what better way to do so, than Rasool Allah ﷺ breaking that rule himself.
It carries more weight, when Rasool Allah ﷺ does it, then when he speaks about it.
So, now Rasool Allah ﷺ married Zainab Bint Jahash(زينب بنت جحش).
There were two rulings here, the first ruling is that there's no more adoption
and second ruling is that a man can marry the wife of his formerly adopted son.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
مَا جَعَلَ اللَّهُ لِرَجُلٍ مِنْ قَلْبَيْنِ فِي جَوْفِهِ ۚ
وَمَا جَعَلَ أَزْوَاجَكُمُ اللَّائِي تُظَاهِرُونَ مِنْهُنَّ أُمَّهَاتِكُمْ ۚ
وَمَا جَعَلَ أَدْعِيَاءَكُمْ أَبْنَاءَكُمْ ۚ
ذَٰلِكُمْ قَوْلُكُمْ بِأَفْوَاهِكُمْ ۖ وَاللَّهُ يَقُولُ الْحَقَّ وَهُوَ يَهْدِي السَّبِيلَ۝
"Allah has not made for any man two hearts in his body, nor has He made your wives
whom you divorce by the Izhaar(إظهار), Your mother's
nor has He made your adopted sons your son's, such is only your manner of speech by your mouth
but Allah tells you, the truth and he shows the right way.
اُدْعُوهُمْ لِآبَائِهِمْ هُوَ أَقْسَطُ عِنْدَ اللَّهِ ۚ
فَإِنْ لَمْ تَعْلَمُوا آبَاءَهُمْ فَإِخْوَانُكُمْ فِي الدِّينِ وَمَوَالِيكُمْ ۚ
وَلَيْسَ عَلَيْكُمْ جُنَاحٌ فِيمَا أَخْطَأْتُمْ بِهِ وَلَٰكِنْ مَا تَعَمَّدَتْ قُلُوبُكُمْ ۚ
وَكَانَ اللَّهُ غَفُورًا رَحِيمًا۝
"Call them by the names of their fathers
This is just her in the sight of Allah but if you know not their fathers names,
call them your brothers in faith, or your Moula's
but there is no blame on you, if you make a mistake there in.
What counts is the intention of your hearts and Allah is oft-forgiving most merciful."
Now just want to make a clarification here,
what is meant by adoption here is not the meaning that we know of adoption today,
when you adopt an orphan, no that's something very good to do it's very reward able.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
أنا وكافل اليتيم كهاتين في الجنة
Rasool Allah ﷺ says, that I will be a neighbor of the one, who sponsors the orphan.
The adoption that is not allowed in Islam
is where the adopted son or daughter, carries the family name of, the ones who adopt them.
In Islam we must carry the names of our ancestors and not carry the names of the ones, who have adopted us.
So, this is just a clarification because the word adoption in English might carry different meaning.
Zainab Bint Jahash(زينب بنت جحش) was a very righteous woman. In fact,
she among the wives of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
she held the very important status with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Ayesha رضي الله عنها says;
None of the wives of Rasool Allah ﷺ used to compete with me, in my status with Rasool Allah ﷺ but Zainab(زينب)
and Rasool Allah ﷺ said, about her.
أسرعكن لحاقاً بي أطولكن يداً
The fastest among you to die after me, will be the one of you with the longest arm,
so Ayesha(عائشه) used to say; We the wives of Rasool Allah ﷺ, would measure our arms
to see who has the longest arm but they didn't understand, what Rasool Allah ﷺ meant?
What he meant by this, by longest arm,
is not literally but it means the one who gives out Sadaqah(صدقه) the most
and that was Zainab Bint Jahash(زينب بنت جحش) and she was the one who died,
the fastest among the wives of Rasool Allah ﷺ, after Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away.
Ayesha(عائشه) said about her;
لم أر امرأة قط خيراً في الدين من زينب، وأتقى لله،
وأصدق حديثاً، وأوصل للرحم، وأعظم صدقة، وأشد ابتذالاً لنفسها في العمل الذي تصدق به وتقربه إلى الله تعالى
ما عدا سورة من حدة كانت فيها، تسرع منها الفيئة
She said: I never seen a woman better than her in her religion,
and more fearful of Allah than her, and more truthful in her speech,
and more attentive to the family relationships than her
and I've never seen a woman who used to give more Sadaqah(صدقه) than her
and she would give herself totally to the deed that she would be doing.
And the only thing with her is that she had a temper,
but she would very soon come back to her normal state, رضي الله عنها.
This marriage of Rasool Allah ﷺ to Zainab(زينب)
has been a point of controversy with the Kuffar(كفار).
They try to use it, as an attacking point against Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And it's interesting to see that there are two particular marriages
that, the Kuffar(كفار) speak about the most
and that is the marriage to Ayesha(عائشه) because of her young age and the marriage to Zainab(زينب)
because they surrounded it with many tales and legends.
And it's interesting to see that these are the particular two marriages that were commanded by Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Because Zainab bint Jahash(زينب بن جحش) would say, to the other wives of Rasool Allah ﷺ
you are married by your parents, while I was married by Allah from on top seven Heavens.
Because Allahعَزّوجَلّ says in Qur'an;
فَزَوَّجْنَاكَهَا
We married we married her, to you.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ when he was married to Ayesha(عائشه) there was no Aqad(عقد) or anything, he just walked in, to her room
because the marriage was performed by Allahعَزّوجَلّ
and with Ayesha رضي الله عنها, it happened because he has seen her in a dream
and we know that the dreams of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) are Wahii(وحي).
So, that is the marriage of Rasool Allah ﷺ to Zainab(زينب).
Also in this period Rasool Allah ﷺ married to Habibah Bint Abi Sufiyan(حبيبه بنت أبي سفيان) the daughter of Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان).
She was in Al-Habasha(ألحبشه) at that time.
She was with the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) in Abyssinia
and her husband Obaidillah Bin Jahash(عبيدالله بن جحش),
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), he was one of the Muhajireen(مهاجرين)
but he had a change of heart, he was deceived by Shaytaan(شيطان),
he became a Murtadd(مرتد) and became a Christian
and he used to make fun of the Muslims and say you are looking with half of your eyes open, while I have seen the light.
He is referring to Christianity, he died as a Murtadd(مرتد).
After he passed away, Rasool Allah ﷺ sent Amr Bin Umayyah Ad-Dhamri(عمرو بن أمية أضَّمْرِيْ) to An-Najjashi(ألنجاشي)
to marry him to Habibah Bint Abi Sufiyaan(حبيبه بنت إبي سفيان) and the marriage was performed
the Walli(وَلِّي) of Habiba(حبيبه) was her cousin, Khalid Bin Saeed Al-Aas(خالد بن سعيد بن العاص)
and the representative of Rasool Allah ﷺ in performing the contract was An-Najjashi(ألنجاشي)
and by this, Umm Habibah(أم حبيبه) became Umm Ul-Mo'mineen(أم المؤمنين)
and Muawiyah رضي الله عنه became the uncle of Al-Mo'mineen(ألمؤمنين) because he is her brother,
رضي الله عنه وعنها والارض الله عزوجل جَميع الصحابه
وَ صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًا